A Guide to the A Guide to the V. Inez Graybeal Roop Collection, 1913-2005
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
V. Inez Graybeal Roop Collection, 1913-2005
Special Collections, James Madison University
5005
4 Hollinger boxes; 1.67 linear feet
The V. Inez Graybeal Roop Collection, 1913-2005, a collection of a notable Harrisonburg Teacher's College [now James Madison University] alumna, contains James Madison University related correspondence, speeches, news clippings, photographs, scrapbooks, and reunion programs, as well as Roop and Graybeal family history.
Inez Graybeal Roop
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
A gift of Inez Graybeal Roop.
Accruals
Through 2006.
Biographical Information
Vivian Inez Graybeal began her studies at Harrisonburg State Teacher's College in 1931 and graduated in 1935. In 1962, Mrs. Roop was elected president of the Richmond Chapter of the Alumni Association and served on the Alumni Association's Board of Directors. She was appointed by Governor Mills Godwin to serve a four year term on Madison College's Board of Visitors beginning in 1974. In 1977, she was awarded the Distinguished Alumnae Service Award. Also in that year, she made the motion petitioning the State Legislature to change the name of the institution to James Madison University. In 1980, she was appointed by Governor John Dalton to serve another four year term on the Board of Visitors. Inez Roop is the namesake of Roop House Alumni Office, dedicated in 1987 and later changed to Cardinal House, and of Roop Hall, dedicated in 1995. When dedicated Roop Hall was the School of Education and psychology building but is now home for mathematics and statistics. Inez Roop is an active participant in her class reunions, and an Emeritus Member of the Alumni Association Board.
Frances "Frankie" Graybeal (Class of 1936) was Inez's younger sister. Both were members of the Glee Club and were featured in joint recitals with Frances as the organist. Frances was also a member of the Lee Literary Society, Alpha Rho Delta, and the Y.W. Cabinet.
Scope and Content
The V. Inez Graybeal Roop Collection, 1913-2005, consists of four Hollinger boxes (1.67 linear feet). The collection consists of nine series: Correspondence; Scholarships and Endowments; Speeches, Awards, and Appointments; Reunions and Bluestone Society; Roop Hall Dedication and Class of 1935 60th reunion; Scrapbooks; State Song Campaign; Roop Family History; and Photographs.
Correspondence, 1971-2005, consists of 21 folders containing letters to and from JMU's President Carrier as well as influential state representatives and senators in Richmond concerning support for Madison College (which became James Madison University in 1977).
Scholarships and Endowments, 1979-2005, consists of three folders containing correspondence and other documents pertaining to the Charles and Bertha Mast Graybeal Scholarship, the Inez G. Roop Professorship in English, and the Ralph and Inez Roop Merit Scholarship.
Speeches, Awards, and Appointments, 1974-2005, consists of one folder containing Mrs. Roop's speeches, appointments, and awards, including the dedications of Roop House in 1987 (later changed to Cardinal House) and accompanying news clippings.
Class Reunions and Bluestone Society, 1948, 1975-2005, consists of three folders containing reunion programs, lists of graduates, and relevant correspondence on the 40th through the 70th reunions of Mrs. Roop's class of 1935. The 60th reunion is not included here.
Roop Hall Dedication and Class of 1935 60th Reunion, 1994-1995, contains two folders of materials relating to the April 21, 1995 naming of the main building for JMU's college of education and psychology "Roop Hall" and the April 22, 1995 60th reunion of the class of 1935. The celebrations of both of these events took place on the same weekend and therefore are included in the same series. Included is a dismantled scrapbook containing materials relating to both events and a folder of various related materials not contained in the scrapbook. Many of the original items in this scrapbook have been photocopied and discarded because they were damaged.
Scrapbooks, 1923-1939, consists of six folders containing varsity basketball scrapbooks [some of which have been photocopied due to the inherent instability of the paper and clippings] which highlight the history of the women's basketball team during this period, and a dismantled scrapbook by Inez's sister, Frances Graybeal, which contained correspondence and ephemera such as greeting cards, invitations and calling cards. One letter lends insight into a mysterious initiation ritual. Photographs were removed and housed with the Photographs series, described below.
State Song Campaign, 1997-2000 and undated, consists of two folders containing correspondence and news clippings chronicling Mrs. Roop's nomination of Dr. John D. Wayland's song "Old Virginia" with music by W. Ruebush to be the Virginia state song.
Roop Family History, 1913-2000, consists of two folders containing biographies of Inez and Ralph Roop, some genealogical information on the Graybeal family, and ephemera relating to the family including report cards for Inez Graybeal and recital programs.
Photographs, 1913-2005, is arranged into two subseries: Personal Photographs and Other Photographs. [Link to image numbers and descriptions.] Two folders of Personal Photographs span 1913-2000 and contain photos of Goodwin, Graybeal and Roop family members. This subseries also contains the pictures taken from Francis Graybeal's dismantled scrapbook. Other Photographs date from c.1920s-2005. These photographs, color and B & W and some with identification written on back, are primarily of Mrs. Roop with classmates and JMU officials at various JMU events, including reunions, dedication of Roop House Alumni Office, and Governor Mills Godwin signing the name change to JMU. Included here are pictures relating to the April 21, 1995 dedication of Roop Hall and the 60th anniversary of the class of 1935. In addition, three panoramic black and white photos of the student body, were transferred from the Roop Collection to the JMU Historic Photograph Collection, with appropriate attribution noted on the reverse of the photographs: 1926 Student Body on steps of quad building, c.1929 Student Body on Quad, 1930 Student Body.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged topically into nine series and chronologically within series: I. Correspondence, 1971-2005 II. Scholarships and Endowments, 1979-2005 III. Speeches, Awards, and Appointments, 1974-2005 IV. Class Reunions and Bluestone Society, 1948, 1975-2005 V. Roop Hall Dedication and Class of 1935 60th Reunion, 1994-1995 VI. Scrapbooks, 1921-1939 VII. State Song Campaign, 1997-2000 and n.d. VIII. Roop Family History, 1913-2000 IX. Photographs, 1913-2005
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Roop, Inez Graybeal, in collaboration with Nancy P. Wheeler. My Life. Richmond, VA: The Author, 2002. Carrier Library Spec. Coll. CS71.R66 2002
Separated Material
Three oversized panoramic black and white photographs, described in Scope and Content note, above.
Contents List (Box:Folder)
- Correspondence, 1971-2005
  - 1971-1973 (1:1)
  - 1974 (1:2)
  - 1975 (1:3)
  - 1976 (1:4)
  - 1977
    - January-June (1:5)
    - July-December (1:6)
  - 1978 (1:7)
  - 1979 (1:8)
  - 1980
    - January-June (1:9)
    - July-December (1:10)
  - 1981 (1:11)
  - 1982-1983 (1:12)
  - 1984 (1:13)
  - 1985 (2:1)
  - 1986-1988 (2:2)
  - 1989-1990 (2:3)
  - 1991-1994 (2:4)
  - 1995-1997 (2:5)
  - 1998-1999 (2:6)
  - 2000-2001 (2:7)
  - 2002-2005 and n.d. (2:8)
- Scholarships and Endowments, 1979-2005
  - 1979-1985 (2:9)
  - 1986-2005 and n.d. (2:10)
  - Thank you notes from students (2:11)
- Speeches, Honors, Awards, and Special Assignments, 1974-2005 (2:12)
- Class Reunions and Bluestone Society, 1948-2005
  - 1948-1975 (3:1)
  - 1985-1986 (3:2)
  - 1987-2005 (3:3)
- Roop Hall Dedication and Class of 1935 60th Reunion, 1994-1995
  - Scrapbook (3:4)
  - Miscellaneous related materials (3:5)
- Scrapbooks, 1923-1939
  - Varsity Basketball:
    - 1923,1926 (3:6)
    - 1929 (3:7)
    - 1932 (3:8)
    - 1934-1936,[1939] (3:9)
  - Francis Graybeal Scrapbook, 1932-1935 and n.d.:
    - Correspondence (3:10)
    - Ephemera (3:11)
- State Song Campaign, 1997-2000, 1997-2000:
  - 1997-1998 (4:1)
  - 1999-2000, n.d. and related newspaper clippings (4:2)
- Roop Family History, 1913-2000:
  - Family History, 1913-2000 (4:3)
  - Ephemera (4:4)
- Photographs, 1913-2005:
  [Link to image numbers and descriptions.]
  - Personal:
    - Francis Graybeal Scrapbook, 1913-1935 [SC5005_FGSB_031 through 068] (4:5)
    - Roop Family Photographs, 1913-2000 [SC5005_RFH_069 through 106] (4:6)
  - Other:
    - Roop Hall Dedication and class of 1935 60th Reunion, 1995 [SC5005_Roopded_001 through 030] (4:7)
    - Miscellaneous Photographs, c. 1920s-2005:
      - Part 1 [SC5005_Other_107 through 154, and 198 through 200] (4:8)
      - Part 2 [SC5005_Other2_155 through 197] (4:9)